Guide to the Sam Brandon Socialist Labor Party Papers TAM.215
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sam Brandon Socialist Labor Party Papers
1900-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Block, Murray
Brandon, Sam
TAM.215
14 Linear Feet in 14 record cartons
Sam Brandon joined the Socialist Labor Party (SLP) as a teenager, and became an organizer for its New York section and chair of its NY State Committee. Expelled in 1927, he helped to found the Socialist Labor Propaganda League, the Industrial Union League (IUL) in 1928, and in 1933 the Industrial Union Party (IUP), and remained its leader, an advocate of the ideas of SLP founder Daniel De Leon, and a critic of the SLP until his death. This collection consists of correspondence and typescripts (principally of Sam Brandon), documents, ephemera, clippings, and some proceedings of various De Leonite organizations. Notable are the files from the 1920s and 1930s which closely document his expulsion from and ongoing disagreements with the SLP, and the founding of the IUL and IUP. Much of the collection covers the years 1970-1984, and documents Brandon’s leading activities in several short-lived De Leonite political groupings. Correspondents include Joseph Brandon, Louis Lazarus, Ralph Muncy, and Arnold Petersen.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Most of the materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. Some materials were arranged by year and re-foldered prior to 2017.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sam Brandon joined the Socialist Labor Party (SLP) as a teenager and became an organizer for its New York section and chair of its NY State Committee. SLP leaders expelled the entire Bronx section in 1927 over political disputes. Brandon, his older brother Joseph, and others formed the Socialist Labor Propaganda League, then the Industrial Union League (IUL) in 1928. In 1933 Sam Brandon founded the Industrial Union Party (IUP). He remained its leader, an advocate of the ideas of SLP founder Daniel De Leon, and a critic of the SLP until his death. Brandon also founded RichLoom, a Brooklyn-based textile manufacturing company, whose profits supported his activism.
Scope and Content Note
The Sam Brandon Socialist Labor Party Papers (1900-1993) consist of correspondence and typescripts (principally of Sam Brandon), documents, ephemera, clippings, and proceedings of various De Leonite and other Socialist organizations. Notable are files from the 1920s and 1930s, which closely document, most importantly through Brandon’s correspondence, his expulsion from and ongoing disagreements with the Socialist Labor Party (SLP), and the founding of the Industrial Union League (IUL) and Industrial Union Party (IUP). The collection holds little material from the years 1940-1969. The remainder of the collection covers the years 1970-1984 and documents Brandon’s leading activities in several short-lived De Leonite political groupings: the Socialist Committee of Correspondence (circa 1969), the Daniel De Leon League (circa 1970), Socialist Reconstruction (circa 1971), and the Revolutionary Industrial Unionists (circa 1979); his leadership of the reactivated IUP; and his criticism of the SLP. Other correspondents include Joseph Brandon, Louis Lazarus, Ralph Muncy, and Arnold Petersen.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to Tamiment Library in 1997 by Murray Block. The accession number associated with this gift is 1997.060. Additional materials found in the repository were incorporated into the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with these materials is 2014.076.
Separated Materials
Issues of the SIU Discussion Bulletins and the Industrial Unionist have been transferred to the library collection.
Socialist parties -- United States.; Socialists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Socialism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Industrial Union Party (U.S.); Block, Murray; Socialist Labor Party; Industrial Union League (U.S.); Brandon, Joseph; Lazarus, Louis; Petersen, Arnold, 1885-1976; De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914
- IUP Party correspondence; publications, clippings, 1974-1993 (Box 1)
- IUP Party correspondence, appeals, mailing lists, 1915-1946, 1972-1993 (Box 2)
- LSR, Socialist Reconstruction correspondence, clippings, De Leonist articles, 1909-1913, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
- Socialist Reconstruction; Ann Arbor conference, 1928-1930, 1965-1978 (Box 4)
- Socialist Reconstruction, IUP correspondence, files by individual name, 1910-1939, 1950-1993 (Box 5)
- IUP correspondence, resolutions; The Weekly People, 1934-1941, 1968-1988 (Box 6)
- IUP correspondence, leaflets, mail lists, minutes, constitution, 1921-1940, 1969-1981 (Box 7)
- IUP, LSR correspondence; files by individual name, 1928-1949, 1975-1992 (Box 8)
- LSR, IUP correspondence; files by individual name, 1968-1989 (Box 9)
- SLP, IUP correspondence, minutes, resolutions; Industrial Unionist; Unity Conference, 1913-1954, 1967-1980 (Box 10)
- IUL, IUP correspondence, clippings, branch reports, 1910-1947 (Box 11)
- SLP, LSR correspondence, minutes, reports; SIU Discussion Bulletins, 1921-1954, 1970-1993 (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1940-1972 (Box 13)
  Arrangement
  Materials in this container were arranged prior to 2017 by date.
- Correspondence, SLP convention proceedings, 1938-1939, 1976-1984 (Box 14)